NYSUT Teacher Education Conference Board Files 6174/009
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Teacher Education Conference Board Files
1964-1996
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kiepper, James
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/009
6.11 cubic feet
6 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
7164021
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
P. Leary, June 15, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 31, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
The Teacher Education Conference Board was created in 1972 in reaction to a proposal by the State Education Department for competency-based teacher education. Officially an independent confederation of educational organizations with its own constitution, TECB was heavily influenced by the teacher's union, New York State United Teachers. NYSUT has a weighted vote on the TECB executive board, paid the salary of its coordinator, and shared the identical address; NYSUT president Tom Hobart served as TECB's vice president, and NYSUT's vice president Antonia Cortese was also an active TECB member. Other organizations on its membership list were the New York Association of Colleges for Teacher Education (NYACTE), the NYS Association of Teacher Educators (ATE), the Council of University Deans (CUD), and the New York State Federation of School Administrators (FSA).
Scope and Contents
1972-1996. Contents are mostly files of staff consultant James Kiepper, whose fee was paid by NYSUT (copies of checks included). Records include voluminous handwritten notes by Kiepper, TECB newsletters and background production materials, meeting agendas and minutes, testimony at Regents hearings, and policy papers on teacher education.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: All other 6174 collections
Teachers' unions -- New York (State); Cortese, Antonia; Hobart, Thomas Y. Jr.; Kiepper, James; New York State United Teachers; New York State United Teachers, Teacher Education Conference Board
7164021
- Salary 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  NY State Education Department printout of salary percentiles for classroom teachers by district experience and degree status
- Salary 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Salary 1979-1980 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Salary 1979-1980 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Salary 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Salary 1977-1978 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Salary 1977-1978 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Salary 1981-1982 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Salary 1981-1982 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Salary 1982-1983 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Salary 1982-1983 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- TEBC Newsletter Vol. 3, No. 2, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Spring
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 13, No. 1, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Fall
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 12, No. 2, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 12, No. 1, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 11, No. 2, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 11, No. 1, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 10, No. 2, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 10, No. 1, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 9, No. 2, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 9, No. 1, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 8, No. 4, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Spring/Summer
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 8, No. 3, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Fall/Winter
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 7, No. 3, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 7, No. 2, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 7, No. 1, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 6, No. 3, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 6, No. 2, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 6, No. 2, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 6, No. 1, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Winter
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 5, No. 2, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Winter/Spring
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 5, No.1, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Fall. Newsletter; list of steps for preparation; additions to newsletter mailing list
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 4, No. 3, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 4, No. 2, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- TECB Position Paper, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  April 1. Press release announcing position paper, "Teaching as a Profession: Toward the Promotion and Support of Competence," re licensing
- Misc. Newsletters, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Various issues, some returned to sender
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 4, No. 1, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 3, No. 2, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Winter. Testimony on Teaching as a Profession, as presented by Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., vice president, Teacher Education Conference Board, to the New York State Board of Regents, February 25, 1981; newsletters
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 3, No. 3, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Spring. To-do list; handwritten list of articles; newspaper clippings with notations "for newsletter"; newsletters, including issues returned to sender
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 3, No. 2, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 4, No. 1, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Winter. Newspaper clippings for newsletter; letter to TECB consultant re spring conference of Confederated Organizations for Teacher Education (COTE); handwritten notes
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 2, No. 1, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 3, No. 1, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 2, No. 2, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 1, No. 8, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 1, No. 8, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- TECB Newsletter Vol. 1, No. 7, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Newsletter Back Issues, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Newsletter, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  May. Handwritten and typed drafts of articles
- Newsletter, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Oct. Handwritten list of articles, by page; note re typo
- Newsletter Misc., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Typed articles; page mock-up; printing request to NYSUT print shop
- TECB Position Papers, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Draft of position paper, "Establishing a Climate for Development of Ethical Behavior," with cover memo, August 12, 1981; draft of same paper, titled, "Morality in the Classroom: Establishing a Climate for Development of Ethical Behavior," with handwritten suggestion for title by reviewer, "Teaching Morals and Ethics," December 11, 1981; draft, March 1982, with other suggested titles; memo with still more title suggestions, May 12, 1982; position paper, "Teaching as a Profession: Toward the Promotion and Support of Competence," April 1980; position paper, "The Effective Teacher," October 1981; press release re "The Effective Teacher," November 30, 1981; print quote for "The Effective Teacher" brochure
- The Effective Teacher Articles and Announcements, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Oct. Newspaper clippings
- Newsletter TECB, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Mock-up for newsletter; correspondence re printing and related costs; print request to NYSUT print shop
- Position Paper-Teaching and Learning with Computers, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  April. Printed brochure
- The Effective Teacher Draft by Maurtiz Johnson, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Brochure by Council for Basic Education, reviewing "The Effective Teacher," March 1982; memo re editing revisions to position paper, April 7, 1981; print quote; clippings from New York Teacher; brochure for "Teaching as a Profession"
- James Kiepper Correspondence, 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Black and white photographs, negatives, and contact sheets
- TECB Annual Meeting-NYC-UFT-J. Kiepper, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  5/15/91. Agenda for annual meeting, May 15, 1991; TECB constitution; draft minutes of TECB meeting of December 14, 1990; press releases; staff consultant report, 1990-91; treasurer's report; budget for 1991-92; Regents discussion item, Status Report on the Career Preparation Validation Study, March 1, 1991; handwritten notes
- TECB Meeting Agenda, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Dec. 14, 1990. Agendas for December 14, 1990, and March 7, 1991, meetings; handwritten notes for minutes of December 14, 1990, and March 8, 1991, meetings
- TECB Conference, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  March 8, 1991. Agenda for Oct 11, 1991, meeting; minutes of annual meeting, May 15, 1991; program for New York Association of Colleges for Teacher Education conference, "Setting the Agenda for the 90's," October 3-4, 1991; brochures and correspondence for other conferences
- TECB Meeting, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  12/31/91. Agenda; minutes of October 11, 1991, meeting; State Education Department press releases; letter of resignation from treasurer and member representing Council of Administrators and Supervisors, noting organization was no longer affiliated with TECB member organization, NYS Federation of School Administrators
- TECB Photographs (Box 2, Folder 51)
  Black and white photographs of meetings of TECB, 1978-1981
- TECB Newsletter (Photo), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  3/10/79. Black and white photograph of meeting
- Dorothy Harrison Biography and Photograph, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  Photograph of Harrison, State Education Department Assistant Commissioner for Policy Analysis; resume of Harrison; photograph of unidentified man, possibly Hadley S. DuPuy; State Education Department press release re appointment of Hadley S. DuPuy as special assistant to Commissioner
- Photographs-Commissioner Ambach's Invitation Meeting on Proposed NTE for NYS, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  1/6/83. Photographs of meeting
- Photographs Taken at NYSUT Board Room Annual Meeting, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  5/3/79. Photographs of meeting
- TECB Newsletter Photographs, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Photograph of meeting; group photo showing NYSUT president/TECB vice president Tom Hobart next to NYSUT vice president Antonia Cortese
- Task Force on Teaching as a Profession-Briefing Book, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  9/10-11/85. Agenda and papers for meeting of Carnegie Forum on Education and the Economy
- Memorandum: Reform of Teacher Education and Certification, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  5/25/77. Memo to Regents from Education Commissioner Ewald Nyquist
- Legalizing Teaching as a Profession, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  Agenda for TECB meeting, May 8-9, 1980; Comments on the Regents Proposal Entitled "Teaching as a Profession and Teacher Competence," prepared for NYSUT members who will testify at Regents hearings, by NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, March 18, 1980; "Teaching as a Profession: A Third View," by Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., president, NYSUT; draft testimony for Daniel Griffiths, resident, TECB, 3/8/80; draft question and answer sheet by NYSUT, "Legalizing Teaching as a Profession"
- Teacher Education Reform, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  TECB press release, "Major Conference Goal to Create Model for Teacher Education Reform," October 30, 1986; Summary Report on the Conference on Teacher Shortage: Challenge for New York State, held April 19, 1985, with cover letter to participants, December 16; agenda for TECB meeting of October 30, 1986; minutes of May 9, 1986, meeting; treasurer's report, October 30, 1986; State Education Department (SED) description of 1986-87 Mentor Teacher-Intern Program; SED booklet, "Strengthening Teaching: A Review of Issues and Programs in New York State," September 1986; TECB booklet, "Collaboration for Teacher Education Reform in New York State: Issues, Strategies and Models: A Workshop for All Educators Interested in Teacher Education in New York State"; Educational Testing Service Test Specifications NTE Core Battery Tests; newspaper clippings and journal articles; correspondence
- COTE Workshop Meeting and Conference, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  9/2/86. Correspondence from Confederated Organizations for Teacher Education; TECB newsletter, vol. 6, no. 2, spring 1984; TECB meeting agenda, October 30, 1986; TECB Executive Committee meeting agenda, September 12, 1986; handwritten notes; workshop brochure
- Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education Conference (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Program; production title sheet
- TECB Conference-Albany Hilton, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  11/16/85. Tentative and final programs, Conference for Teacher Educators: Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education; program for COTE/TECB workshop at Albany Quality Inn, October 31, 1986
- Workshop on Teacher Education "Issues, Strategies and Models", 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Mock-up of title; tip sheet, "Preparing and Presenting Testimony"
- TECB Conference, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  11/16/85. Correspondence re November 16 meeting; handwritten notes; agenda for conference on teacher shortage, April 19, 1985; agenda for TECB Executive Committee meeting of June 28, 1985
- TECB Conference Albany Hilton Schedule/Registration Form, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Conference announcement, program, and registration form for "Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education," November 16, 1985; agenda for TECB meeting, November 15, 1985
- TECB Conference Albany Hilton-Attendance List, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  11/16/85. Testimony of NYSUT Regarding the Regents Hearings on the Proposed Amendments to the Certificate Requirements for Elementary and Secondary Academic Areas, October 16, 1986; workshop program, "Collaboration for Teacher Education Reform in New York State: Issues, Strategies and Models"; TECB press release, "Major Conference Goal to Create Model for Teacher Education Reform," October 30, 1986; conference announcement and program, "Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education," November 16, 1985; summary report on the Conference on the Teacher Shortage: Challenge for New York State, held April 19, 1985; attendance lists
- TECB Conference Tentative Program, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Conference announcement and program, "Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education," November 16, 1985
- TECB Conference-Expenses, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  11/16/85. Program for teacher educators, "Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education"; expense statement from Albany Hilton to NYSUT; letter from NYS Association of Teacher Educators re possible joint meeting of executive boards
- TECB Conference Albany Hilton Registration Forms, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  11/16/85. Filled-in individual registration forms for conference, Impact of the Reform Movement on Teacher Education; lists of invitees
- TECB Bulk Mailing List, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Computer printout
- TECB-Mental Health Education, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Letters from Roger Burton, professor at SUNY Buffalo, to James Kiepper, staff consultant for TECB, and Gerald Mager, School of Education, Syracuse University, re research paper, "Establishing a Climate for Development of Ethical Behavior," October 1981; articles from New York Times and Psychology Today re book by Lawrence Kohlberg, "The Philosophy of Moral Development," August 1981; mental health tips for teachers; NYU brochure, "How to Talk to Your Children about AIDS"
- TECB Executive Committee, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  5/5/1989. Agenda for annual meeting; agenda for TECB Executive Committee; proposed calendar, 1989-90; budget, 1989-90; treasurer's report, May 5, 1989; TECB newsletter, vol. 8, no. 4, spring/summer 1989; handwritten notes
- TECB Newsletter, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Fall. Newsletters for fall 1987 and spring 1988; handwritten list of articles and other notes; text of articles
- TECB Misc. Conferences and Articles, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  TECB Plans and Activities for 1982-83, November 12, 1982; TECB memorandum to Tom Hobart from Jim Kiepper for discussion only, Critique of Teaching as a Profession for the Regents, March 31, 1980; handwritten notes
- TECB Newsletter, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Spring. Handwritten list of article by page; State Education Department newsletter, "Learning in New York," April 1985
- TECB Dinner and Meeting Steuben Athletic Club, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  11/16/85. 1985-86 membership list; document, History and Background of the Teacher Education Conference Board; TECB constitution; revised calendar, 1985-86; handwritten notes
- TECB Annual Meeting Minutes, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Agenda of annual meeting, September 28, 1987; minutes; minutes of TECB Executive Committee meeting of May 5, 1988; minutes of meetings of May 5-6, 1988, December 9, 1988,and February 16-17, 1989; program for conference for teacher educators, Impact of Reform Movement on Teacher Education
- TECB-Various Articles Teacher Reform, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Article, "The New Right and the Schools," American Educator, fall 1982, with cover letter from NYSUT vice president and TECB member Antonia Cortese; other articles from American Educator, Education Week, and Carnegie Quarterly
- TECB-Treasurer's Reports, Minutes, Articles, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Minutes of May 3, 1985, meeting; handwritten notes; newspaper clippings; Journal of AACTE/NYS (American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education of New York State), vol. 1, spring 1985
- First National NBPTS Forum, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Selected summary of presenters' remarks, First National NBPTS Forum, July 17-19, 1989
- Politics of Educational Reform, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Draft paper by Robert Koff, dean, School of Education, SUNY Albany; newspaper clipping re Koff's remarks at conference; other clippings
- Education Reform, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Regent's Proposed Action Plan to Improve Elementary and Secondary Education Results in New York, August 1983; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Jericho High School-Robert Hoffman, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Article in Quest, "After the Recession," interview with futurist Peter Schwartz; conference program for World Future Society, "The Next Millennium: Unlearning the Twentieth Century, November 6-8, 1980; newsletter by Long Island Council for the Social Studies, fall 1979; letter to Jim Kiepper (?) from Jericho Free School District teacher Robert Hoffman
- TECB Position Paper Topics-Future Topics, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Memo from Kiepper to TECB suggesting topics for position papers; handwritten notes
- Investing in People for the Information Age-The Futurist-Gary Hart, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Feb. Article clipping
- Literary Education, 1964-1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  The English Composition Test with Essay, by Admissions Testing Program of the College Board; Pilot Program in Liberal Education; brief glossary of terms used in critical reading and literary analysis; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Teaching-Related Articles, Papers, Magazines, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  Issues of Time (October 10, 1983) and Newsweek (May 9, 1983, and September 24, 1984); paper by Roger Burton, SUNY Buffalo, "Creating a Moral Climate in the Classroom," March 1982; handwritten notes
- TECB-Position Description-Staff Consultant, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  Job description; article from Children's Playmate magazine re breaking gender career roles, April 1980
- Lecture at Geneseo, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  Memo to TECB from staff consultant James Kiepper with attached copies of bills submitted for action by the NYS legislature on teaching as a profession, March 10, 1981; State Education Department press release, Regents Require Examination for Teacher Certification or Licensing, April 24, 1981; paper, "Establishing a Climate for Development of Ethical Behavior," Roger Burton, SUNY Buffalo, July 1981; draft speech by Daniel Griffiths, dean of NYU School of Education; handwritten outline of speech, to-do list, and other notes; newspaper clippings re teacher attrition
- TECB-Misc., 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  Minutes of TECB meeting of May 12, 1977; draft of memo from staff consultant Kiepper to Superintendent of Schools re joining mailing list for newsletter
- TECB Expenses, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Treasurer's report, March 9, 1984; proposed budget 1984-85; invoices; handwritten notes
- COTE Conference, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Fall. Program for Confederated Organizations for Teacher Education conference, "The 80's Teacher Education in the Pressure Cooker"; COTE newsletter, fall 1980; conference announcement
- TECB Various Meetings and Programs (1 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  TECB meeting minutes; minutes of Board of Regents; State Education Department document, "Invitation to React to Regents Tentative Proposal on Teaching as a Profession and Teacher Competence," March 7, 1980; reaction by Daniel Griffiths, president of TECB, at public hearing, April 9; revised Commissioner's recommendations
- TECB Various Meetings and Programs (2 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  Minutes of the Board of Regents; minutes of TECB annual meetings
- TECB, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  Agenda for annual meeting, May 24, 1993; staff consultant report, 1992-93; proposed calendar, 1993-94; treasurer's report, May 1993; budget, 1993-94; minutes of TECB meeting of March 6, 1992; membership list as of March 1992 and tentative list of members to review; abstract proposal, May 19, 1993; press release from governor's office (Mario Cuomo) re Moreland Act investigation of education system spending, May 17, 1993; Northeast Common Market Project Update, April 22, 1993; DeWitt Wallace-Reader's Digest Study Conference report, November 1992; materials from Regents re teacher certification; newspaper clippings; Testimony on Teaching as a Profession as presented by Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., vice president, TECB, to the NYS Board of Regents, February 25, 1981
- TECB Meeting Photographs, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 37)